<chapter id="limitations">
  <title>Limitations</title>

  <sect1 id="limitations_global"><title>Global limitations</title>
    <para>
      &LIBGDA;'s global limitations are:
      <sect2 id="threads"><title>Multi threaded environment</title>
	<para>&LIBGDA; is not thread safe. However it supports working with threads as long as any object 
	  (except otherwise stated) created by the API is used by one single thread (that is there is no
	  situation when two threads try to access the same object at the same time). Exceptions are:
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para>&LIBGDA;'s <link linkend="init_config">configuration</link> can be accessed from any thread</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>Any object which implements the <link linkend="GdaLockable">GdaLockable</link> interface 
		can be accessed from any thread. However 
		one can use the <link linkend="gda-lockable-lock">gda_lockable_lock()</link> method to specifically 
		lock an object's usage (especially when getting and
		setting properties before or after calling methods).</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>Any <link linkend="GdaConnection">GdaConnection</link> object can be accessed from any thread 
		(that object implements the <link linkend="GdaLockable">GdaLockable</link> interface). Also
		some database providers may impose other limitations (inherited from the database's specific client APIs)
		such as only one thread can use the connection object, or even that only one thread can use the database
		provider.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>Any <link linkend="GdaAttributesManager">GdaAttributesManager</link> can safely be accessed from
		any thread.</para></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
	
	<para>Note that multi threading support is still at an early stage and may contain bugs</para>
      </sect2>
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="limitations_mysql"><title>For MySQL</title>
    <sect2><title>Multi threaded environment</title>
      <para>
	If MySQL client was not compiled with the <option>--enable-thread-safe-client</option> flag, 
	then the database provider will only allow
	connections to be opened from the thread which initializes &LIBGDA;. Otherwise there is no limitation.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2><title>Statements execution</title>
      <para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>It is not possible to execute a SELECT statement with invalid parameters and
	      with the GDA_STATEMENT_MODEL_ALLOW_NOPARAM flag as this feature is currently not implemented.
	      </para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="limitations_oracle"><title>For Oracle</title>
    <para>
      The following limitations apply to Oracle databases accessed via Libgda:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>At the moment tables' fields schema information retrieval is very slow, so as a work around, use a dictionary
	to store the database schema and do incremental updates on modified/created tables.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="limitations_postgres"><title>For PostgreSQL</title>
    <para>
      The following limitations apply to PostgreSQL databases accessed via Libgda:
    </para>
    <sect2><title>BLOB handling</title>
      <para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>Postgres uses the "Oid" data type to internally store BLOBs, but this type is also used
	      to store other information within the database. Libgda assumes that any column of type "Oid" represents a
	      blob. If this is not the case, then you must cast it to the correct data type within your SQL query (for example
	      as "SELECT oid::varchar FROM...")</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>&LIBGDA; does not try to avoid orphaned BLOBs, to solve the problem of orphaned BLOBs, set up
	      the "lo" extension from PöstgreSQL's contrib, and/or use the "vacuumlo" also from the contrib.</para>
	  <para>Note that in the future the PostgreSQL's provider will have an option to ensure that there are no
	    orphaned BLOBs itself.</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>BLOB manipulations can only occur within a transaction, 
	      so you should start a transaction before any operation
	      on BLOBs, otherwise Libgda will automatically start one</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2><title>Last inserted row's values</title>
      <para>
	The <link linkend="gda-connection-statement-execute-non-select">gda_connection_statement_execute_non_select()</link>'s last_insert_row attribute will return a <link linkend="GdaSet">GdaSet</link> object only if the table has OIDs.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2><title>Multi threaded environment</title>
      <para>
	If PostgreSQL was not compiled with the <option>--enable-thread-safety</option> flag, 
	then the database provider will only allow
	connections to be opened from the thread which initializes &LIBGDA;. Otherwise there is no limitation.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2><title>Statements execution</title>
      <para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>It is not possible to execute a SELECT statement with invalid parameters and
	      with the GDA_STATEMENT_MODEL_ALLOW_NOPARAM flag if the GDA_STATEMENT_MODEL_CURSOR_FORWARD
	      flag is also specified</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="limitations_sqlite"><title>For SQLite</title>
    <para>
      The following limitations apply to SQLite databases accessed via Libgda:
    </para>
    <sect2><title>Last inserted row's values</title>
      <para>
	The <link linkend="gda-connection-statement-execute-non-select">gda_connection_statement_execute_non_select()</link>'s last_insert_row attribute uses the hidden "_ROWID_" column for each table, but it may fail if the table has a column with the same name.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2><title>Date and time</title>
      <para>
	As SQLite stores dates and times as strings, &LIBGDA; only handles dates in the format recommended by SQLite,
	which is "YYYY-MM-DD" for dates, "HH:MM:SS" for times and "YYYY-MM-DD HH:MM:SS" for timestamps (see 
	<ulink url="http://www.sqlite.org/cvstrac/wiki?p=DateAndTimeFunctions">SQLite's documentation</ulink>).
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2><title>Multi threaded environment</title>
      <para>
	No limitation if sqlite has been compiled with the SQLITE_THREADSAFE=1 flag (which is the case for the
	embedded version of SQLite). If the system installed SQLite is used and if it was not compiled using that
	flag, then &LIBGDA; sets the SQLite library in a state where multi threading is fully supported.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="limitations_sqlcipher"><title>For SqlCipher</title>
    <para>
      The following limitations apply to SQLite database accessed through the SQLCipher database
      provider. The SQLCipher database provider allows one to connect to a database encrypted using the
      <ulink url="http://www.zetetic.net/code/sqlcipher">SQLCipher</ulink> adaptations to the SQLite
      database.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <link linkend="limitations_sqlite">SQLite provider's limitations</link> also apply in this context
      and it is also currently not possible to uncrypt an encrypted database.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="limitations_jdbc"><title>For JDBC based providers</title>
    <para>
      The following limitations apply to databases accessed via Libgda through a JDBC driver. When loading
      the database providers, &LIBGDA; creates a JDBC provider per JDBC driver found (to work at all it
      needs to load the Java Virtual Machine (JVM) runtime first).
    </para>

    <sect2><title>JDBC drivers' location</title>
      <para>
	JDBC drivers (".jar" files) are searched for in the following locations:
	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem><para>in each directory or JAR file in the <envar>CLASSPATH</envar> environment variable
	      (if set)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>in the <filename>$HOME/.local/share/libgda/config</filename> directory (or 
	      <filename class="directory">$HOME/.libgda</filename> if if exists and
	      <filename>$HOME/.local/share/libgda/config</filename> does not)</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2><title>Last inserted row's values</title>
      <para>
	TODO.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2><title>Multi threaded environment</title>
      <para>
	No specific limitation.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
</chapter>
