<chapter id="provider-notes">
  <title>Provider's notes</title>

  <sect1 id="provider_notes_oracle"><title>For Oracle</title>
    <para>
      The following arguments are used to connect to an Oracle database:
      <table frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1" align="justify">
          <thead>
	    <row>
              <entry>Argument name</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
              <entry>Required</entry>
	    </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
	    <row>
              <entry>DB_NAME</entry>
              <entry>Service name: global database name entered during database creation (it combines a database name with a domain name), can be left empty to connect to the default database.</entry>
              <entry>No</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
              <entry>HOST</entry>
              <entry>Database server: host on which the database server is running</entry>
              <entry>Yes</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
              <entry>PORT</entry>
              <entry>Port: database server port (leave this field empty for the default 1521 port)</entry>
              <entry>No</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
              <entry>SCHEMA</entry>
              <entry>Schema: Name of the schema to use. If not specified, the schema defaults to that of the connected user.</entry>
              <entry>No</entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>
      Note however all the arguments above can be replaced by a single TNSNAME argument (see
      the "Oracle Database Net Services Administrator's Guide" for more information about defining
      connection identifiers).
    </para>
    <para>
      Also refer to the <link linkend="limitations_oracle">Oracle's provider's limitations</link>.
    </para>
  </sect1>

<sect1 id="provider_notes_sqlite"><title>For SQLite</title>
    <para>
      The following arguments are used to connect to an SQLite database:
      <table frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1" align="justify">
          <thead>
	    <row>
              <entry>Argument name</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
              <entry>Required</entry>
	    </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
	    <row>
              <entry>DB_NAME</entry>
              <entry>Name of the database. This should be the name of the database file without
	      the ".db" extension. However when opening a database, if a file named after the DB_NAME
	      value exists then it is used (so beware, for example if DB_NAME is set to "mydb" and a file
	      named "mydb" exists but is not an SQLite database, then an error will occur)</entry>
              <entry>Yes</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
              <entry>DB_DIR</entry>
              <entry>The directory where the database file is; if not specified, the current working
	      directory is used.</entry>
              <entry>No</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
              <entry>EXTRA_FUNCTIONS</entry>
              <entry>If set to TRUE (or unspecified), then some extra functions defined by &LIBGDA; are added. The functions are:
	      <function>gda_file_exists()</function>, <function>gda_hex_print()</function>,
	      <function>gda_hex()</function>, <function>gda_rmdiacr()</function>,
	      <function>gda_lower()</function> and <function>gda_upper()</function>; see below 
	      for more information about them.
	      </entry>
              <entry>No</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
              <entry>EXTRA_COLLATIONS</entry>
              <entry>If set to TRUE (or unspecified), then some extra collations defined by &LIBGDA; are added.
	      They are:
	      <function>LOCALE</function> (the strings are compared taking into account UTF8 sorting and the
	      current locale) and <function>DCASE</function> (before comparison, all the diacritical
	      signs (for example accents) are removed from the strings and they are converted to lower case).
	      </entry>
              <entry>No</entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>
    </para>

    <sect2>
      <title>The <function>gda_file_exists()</function> function</title>
      <para>
	This function accepts a filename as argument, and returns 0 if the file with that filename does not
	exist, or 1 if it does.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>The <function>gda_hex_print()</function> function</title>
      <para>
	This function accepts at most 2 arguments, in that order:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>a blob value</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>a length (not mandatory)</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
	It returns a string suitable to be printed (where all the non ascii characters are converted to
	the "\xyz" syntax where "xyz" is the decimal value of the character), limited to the specified
	length if any. 
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>The <function>gda_hex()</function> function</title>
      <para>
	This function accepts at most 2 arguments, in that order:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>a blob value</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>a length (not mandatory)</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
	It returns a hex dump string of the blob value, limited to the specified length if any.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>The <function>gda_rmdiacr()</function> function</title>
      <para>
	This function accepts at most 2 arguments, in that order:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>a string value</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>a case conversion to do (not mandatory), as a string which must be
	  'upper' or 'lower'</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
	It returns a string where all the diacritical signs (for example accents) from the input string,
	and optionally converts the string to upper or lower case if specified. This function takes into
	account the current locale and is useful to do some text search.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>The <function>gda_upper()</function> and <function>gda_lower()</function> functions</title>
      <para>
	These function accept one string argument and convert it to upper or lower case, taking into account
	the locale (the standard SQLite <function>upper()</function> and <function>lower()</function>
	functions only operating on ASCII characters).
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <para>
      Also refer to the <link linkend="limitations_sqlite">SQLite's provider's limitations</link>.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="provider_notes_sqlcipher"><title>For SQLCipher</title>
  <para>
    The SQLCipher database provider allows one to connect to a database encrypted using the
    <ulink url="http://www.zetetic.net/code/sqlcipher">SQLCipher</ulink> adaptations to the SQLite
    database. This section deals about how to manage the passphrase associated with a database file, please
    also consult the information <ulink url="http://www.zetetic.net/code/sqlcipher">provided by SQLCipher</ulink>
    before attempting to use this database provider.
  </para>
  <para>
    The first noticeable point is that any SQLite database file can be opened using the SQLCipher and
    will remain useable with the "standard" SQLite provider as long as it's not explicitely encrypted using
    a passphrase.
  </para>
  <sect2>
    <title>How to create and encrypted database</title>
    <para>
      To create an encrypted database, you can use the <application>gda-sql</application> and when prompted
      enter the requested passphrase, as:
      <programlisting><![CDATA[prompt> gda-sql-4.0 "SQLCipher://DB_NAME=testcrypt"
Welcome to the GDA SQL console, version 4.1.11

Type: .copyright to show usage and distribution terms
      .? for help with internal commands
      .q (or CTRL-D) to quit
      (the '.' can be replaced by a '\')
      or any query terminated by a semicolon

Opening connection 'c0' for: SQLCipher://DB_NAME=testcrypt
	Password for 'c0':]]></programlisting>
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>How to encrypt an existing database</title>
    <para>
      To encrypt an existing database, connect to the database using the SQLCipher provider and execute the
      following SQL command (replace the passphrase with the requested passphrase):
      <programlisting>PRAGMA key = 'passphrase';</programlisting>
      setting the requested passphrase which will be later required to reopen the database. This step
      prevents opening the database file by the "standard" SQLite provider.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>How to change the passphrase of an encrypted database</title>
    <para>
      To change an encrypted database's passphrase, open a connection to the database and enter the following
      SQL command (replace the passphrase with the requested new passphrase):
      <programlisting>PRAGMA rekey = 'passphrase';</programlisting>
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <para>
    Also refer to the <link linkend="provider_notes_sqlite">SQLite's provider's notes</link>,
    and <link linkend="limitations_sqlcipher">SQLCipher provider's limitations</link>.
  </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="provider_notes_ldap"><title>For LDAP</title>
    <para>
      The LDAP provider maps LDAP searches to &LIBGDA;'s data models, with the following design choices:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>A data model column is created for each attibute the LDAP search returns, plus one
	column for the DN (Distinguished name), as the 1st column of each search;
	so if no attribute is requested, the resulting data model
	will only contain one column for the DN</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>If not otherwise specified, the data type of each data model column is determined
	by the data type of the corresponding column attribute</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Multi valued attributes are by default handled as an invalid data, but it is possible to
	specify instead to report a NULL value, or an array in a CSV notation.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>For performances reasons, some data is cached (unless the "USE_CACHE" connection
	variable is set to FALSE). Cache files are in the users's home directory, as per the
	<ulink url="http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Specifications/basedir-spec">XDG Base Directory Specification</ulink></para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      For more information, see the <link linkend="GdaDataModelLdap">GdaDataModelLdap</link> and
      the <link linkend="GdaLdapConnection">GdaLdapConnection</link> objects.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  
</chapter>
